<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Survival Analysis on Theodor Adrian Balan</title>
    <link>https://teddybalan.github.io/tags/survival-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Survival Analysis on Theodor Adrian Balan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Theodor Adrian Balan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/survival-analysis/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD thesis: Advances in frailty models</title>
      <link>https://teddybalan.github.io/project/advances-frailty/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://teddybalan.github.io/project/advances-frailty/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-are-frailty-models&#34;&gt;What are frailty models?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine we have a device that ticks every now and then, and denote the number of ticks up to time $t$ as
$N(t)$. Broadly speaking, the goal of survival analysis is to determine the &lt;em&gt;intensity&lt;/em&gt; of this process,
so as to answer how likely it is that, after observing this device for a while, we would expect another
tick to happen in the next period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quantity is usually modeled like:
$$
h(t) = h_0(t) \exp(\beta^\top \mathbf{x}(t))
$$
where $h_0(t)$ is a &lt;em&gt;baseline&lt;/em&gt; intensity and $\mathbf{x}(t)$ represents a number of possibly time dependent factors,
or knowledge that we have about $N(t)$, that we believe it might influence the intensity. This is called a
&lt;em&gt;proportional intensity&lt;/em&gt; model and has been developed from the 70s.
The term &lt;em&gt;survival analysis&lt;/em&gt; comes from the situation where $N$ can only click once, usually representing death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frailty models come in for two big reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;usually we do not know &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the factors that may influence $h(t)$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;when several devices are related in a way that is difficult to quantify (thinking similar unmeasured genetic build or similar environmental conditions that can&amp;rsquo;t be measured), we know that the tickers are related, and this information must be incorporated somehow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in essence we claim that there is an unobservable variable $Z$ that affects $h(t)$. If we had observed $Z$ (which we don&amp;rsquo;t), then the intensity of $N(t)$ would be
$$
h(t) = Z h_0(t) \exp(\beta^\top \mathbf{x}(t)).
$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can work out that this is essentially a linear random intercept mixed model for the log-intensity. It turns out that, compared to regular linear mixed models, this leads to a large number of surprising results, while the estimation is in general challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of models is still controversial to some extent, as they do involve a healthy dose of speculation. However, often, we are interested in the &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;/em&gt; treatment effect rather than the &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt;, that is, the effect on the individual and not that on the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-the-purpose-of-my-phd&#34;&gt;What is the purpose of my PhD?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of my PhD is to study how these things relate in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/sim.6913/full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Score test for association between recurrent events and a terminal event&lt;/a&gt;, we developed, well&amp;hellip; a score test to see whether a recurrent event process and a terminal event process are associated or not. The same idea can be used to test for dependent censoring of a recurrent event process. This is partially implemented in the &lt;code&gt;frailtyEM&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/sim.6968/full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ascertainment correction in frailty models for recurrent events data&lt;/a&gt;, we looked at what happens when you select individual histories of recurrent events based on a number of events having happened in a certain calendar time period. We propose a fix for that and an iterative estimation method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=frailtyEM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;frailtyEM: An R Package for Estimating Semiparametric Shared Frailty Models&lt;/a&gt;, we implemented a general estimation method for semi-parametric frailty models. It&amp;rsquo;s the only package (to my knowledge) that estimates gamma, positive stable, inverse Gaussian and a number of other distributions for the random effect, for semi-parametric shared frailty models. The original motivation was to have an R package that does things in a consistent way and is well documented, and many other ideas transformed it into what it is. For example, you can get a predicted survival curve with the frailty integrated out for an individual with time-dependent covariates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also working on a number of other projects that will make it into this list as they get closer to completion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MSc Statistical Science alumni video</title>
      <link>https://teddybalan.github.io/project/master-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://teddybalan.github.io/project/master-video/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MSc thesis</title>
      <link>https://teddybalan.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://teddybalan.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
