<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homes on Theodor Balan</title>
    <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homes on Theodor Balan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Theodor Balan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tbalan.github.io/home/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tbalan.github.io/home/about/</guid>
      <description>Biography I am a PhD student in the department of Medical Statistics and Bioinformatics at Leiden University Medical Center. My work is centered around complex time-to-event data, mostly in the field of random effect (frailty models) in survival analysis. In my spare time, I like to put my skills to use for good causes. I am the co-author and maintainer of the R packages frailtyEM and dynfrail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software</title>
      <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tbalan.github.io/home/software/</guid>
      <description>frailtyEM is an R package that may be used for fitting shared frailty models. For a Breslow-type non-parametric baseline hazard, several frailty distributions are supported: gamma, inverse Gaussian, positive stable, PVF-family. Both clustered failures and recurrent events are supported, and prediction curves are easily obtained.
The stable version is on CRAN and development version on GitHub. For a more detailed presentation of models and methods, as well as an overview of the implemented estimation approach, I wrote a comprehensive vignette for the package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tbalan.github.io/home/projects/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks &amp; posters</title>
      <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tbalan.github.io/home/talks/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tbalan.github.io/home/publications/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tbalan.github.io/home/teaching/</guid>
      <description>On 5 November 2017, Hein Putter and I will give a day-course on Frailty models: theory and practice for the The Czech National Group of the International Society for Clinical Biostatistics. More information about registration is available on the course website.
At the XXIXth International Biometrical Conference (Barcelona, 2018), Hein Putter and I will give the half-day short course Frailty models: theory and practice. This will be part of the Statistics in Practice session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://tbalan.github.io/home/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tbalan.github.io/home/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>